Guide to the Bernard Siegel Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Bernard Siegel papers
1941-1992
SC0497
Siegel, Bernard J. (Bernard Joseph), 1913-
5 Linear feet
These papers include course materials, lecture notes, and students' papers from classes he taught, 1965-87; papers and articles he wrote, 1951-77; research proposals, including those for his study of Parma, Italy; correspondence pertaining to Stanford in Italy, 1970-72; his professional correspondence, largely outgoing, 1963-1992; and photographs from a saint's day celebration in Picuris Pueblo, ca. 1957. His professional correspondence pertains to research projects, publications, his students' progress on their projects, as well as occasional personal matters. Correspondents include James T. Siegel, Teigo Yoshida, Ruth Landes, Allen W. Johnson, William B. Rodgers, Arnold Strickon, Alan R. Beals, June Nash, George Spindler, Mary Kelsey, and Meyer Fortes.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Bernard Siegel, 1995, 2004.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Bernard Siegel came to Stanford University as assistant professor in anthropology in 1947. In 1954 he was appointed full professor and served as chairman of the department from 1961 to 1964. In 1989, he was appointed professor emeritus. From 1972 to 1975 he was the director of Stanford's Center for Latin American Studies. He has done field research in Brazil, Portugal, and Italy and in Native American pueblos in the United States. Since 1972, he has been the editor of the ANNUAL REVIEW OF ANTHROPOLOGY and is the author of many scholarly articles.
Description of the Collection
These papers include course materials, lecture notes, and students' papers from classes he taught, 1965-87; papers and articles he wrote, 1951-77; research proposals, including those for his study of Parma, Italy; correspondence pertaining to Stanford in Italy, 1970-72; his professional correspondence, largely outgoing, 1963-1992; and photographs from a saint's day celebration in Picuris Pueblo, ca. 1957. His professional correspondence pertains to research projects, publications, his students' progress on their projects, as well as occasional personal matters. Correspondents include James T. Siegel, Teigo Yoshida, Ruth Landes, Allen W. Johnson, William B. Rodgers, Arnold Strickon, Alan R. Beals, June Nash, George Spindler, Mary Kelsey, and Meyer Fortes.
Access Terms
Beals, Alan R.; Fortes, Meyer.; Johnson, Allen W.; Kelsey, Mary.; Landes, Ruth, 1908-1991; Nash, June C., 1927-; Rodgers, William Blackstock III.; Siegel, Bernard J. (Bernard Joseph), 1913-; Siegel, James T., 1937-; Spindler, George Dearborn; Stanford University. Center for Latin American Studies.; Stanford University. Department of Anthropology. Faculty.; Stanford University. Overseas Study Program.; Strickon, Arnold.; Yoshida, Teigo, 1923-; Anthropology--Study and teaching.; Anthropology.; Parma (Italy).; Photoprints.; Picuris (N.M.)--Social life and customs.; Tigua Indians--Social life and customs.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Anthropology 106/206: Structure and Change in Rural Latin America (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anthropology 108: Peoples of Europe (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anthropology 108: reprints (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anthropology 108: student papers (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anthropology 127: Mediterranean Anthropology: syllabi and exams (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anthropology 127: lecture notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anthropology 127: lecture notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anthropology 127: lecture notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anthropology 127: reprints (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Anthropology 127: William A. Douglass, "South Italian Familism" (reprint) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Anthropology 127: student enrollment and exams (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Anthropology 127: sourcebook (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Anthropology 144: Social and Political Movements: course preparation (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Anthropology 144: course syllabi and bibliography (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Anthropology 144: James Fernandez, "African Religious Movements" (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - (unpublished reprint) (Box 1)
  - Anthropology 144: misc. reprints and fragments (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Anthropology 144: student papers (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Anthropology 146: Urban Problems and Issues in Anthropological Perspective (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Anthropology 147: Peasant Migrations and Social Change: course syllabi and exams (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Anthropology 147: lecture notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Anthropology 147: lecture notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Anthropology 147: lecture notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Anthropology 147: reprints: A-J (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Anthropology 147: reprints: K-R (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Anthropology 147: reprints: S-Z (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Anthropology 163: Cultural Dynamics (1965): course materials (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Anthropology 163: lecture notes (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Anthropology 163: sources and reprints (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Anthropology 207: Latin America (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Anthropology 235: Cultural Dynamics (1987) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Stanford Faculty Reports, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Stanford dissertation: Midori Arima, "An Ethnographic Study of the Bonin Islands," outline and correspondence (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Stanford dissertation: Janeen Arnold Costa, "Tradition and Change in Peasant Societies," proposal and correspondence (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Stanford dissertation: Regina Campos, "Brazilian Psychologists and their Impact on Primary Education," proposal and correspondence (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Stanford dissertation: Miguel Diaz-Barriga: "Urban Community Politics in Mexico City," proposal (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Stanford dissertation: Merielle Flood: "The Economics of Gender in a Tourist City," proposal and correspondence (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Stanford dissertation: Rosemary Henge, "Informal Teaching and Learning in a Greek Community," proposal and correspondence (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Stanford dissertation: Allen Willard Johnson, "Economics and Dependence...In Brazil," abstract (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Stanford dissertation: Madhuri Mathema, "Improving Women's Lives: A Case Study in Nepal," proposal drafts (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Professional: symposia, etc.
    - European Peasant Society Symposium: papers, 1951-1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Comparative Civilizations Seminar, Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, Feb.-Mar. 1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Comparative Civilizations Seminar, Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, Feb.-Mar. 1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Stanford in Italy: correspondence 1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Stanford in Italy: minutes 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Stanford in Italy: correspondence 1971 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Stanford in Italy: minutes 1971 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Stanford in Italy: correspondence 1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Migration in Latin America Seminar, 1976 memorandum and reprint, "Conflict, Parochialism and Social Differentiation in Portuguese Society" (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Professional: Siegel articles
    - "The Contestado Rebellion" reprint, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Defensive Cultural Adaptation" draft, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "High Anxiety Levels...A Psycho-Cultural Hypothesis" (from Social Forces, 1955) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Residence, Households and Kinship...Estates of Northern Brazil," n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "Social Structure...In Rural Brazil and Portugal" (Sociologico, 1958) (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "Some Structure Implications...in New Mexico" (reprinted from AES, 1959) (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Urban Research in Milan: Some Technical Considerations," n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Professional: Siegel proposals
    - "The Role of the School as a Social System...in Northern Italy" draft proposal (1972-3) (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Parma Valley Proposal: "Land, Labor and Family" (draft 1, 1975) (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Parma Valley Proposal: "Migration and Adaptation in Southern Italy," n.d. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Parma Valley Proposal: (1976) (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Parma Valley Proposal: draft 3 (1978) (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Parma Valley Proposal: revision (1978) (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Parma Valley Proposal: draft 4 (1979) (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Parma Valley Proposal: field research (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Parma Valley Proposal: Italian sources (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Siegel correspondence: 1963 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Siegel correspondence: Jan.-May 1964 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Siegel correspondence: Jun.-Dec. 1964 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Siegel correspondence: 1966 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Siegel correspondence: 1967 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Siegel correspondence: Jan.-May 1968 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Siegel correspondence: Jun.-Dec. 1968 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Siegel correspondence: Jan.-May 1969 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Siegel correspondence: Jun.-Dec. 1969 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Siegel correspondence: 1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Siegel correspondence: 1971 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Siegel correspondence: 1972 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Siegel correspondence: 1973 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Siegel correspondence: 1974 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Siegel correspondence: 1975-1985 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Siegel correspondence: 1986-1989 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Siegel correspondence: 1990-1992 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Japanese educational reform: reports and commentaries by others (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Japanese rural society: English summaries of book by Tadashi Fukutake (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Japanese social structures: translations of articles (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photos
    - Picuris pueblo photos, San Lorenzo Saints Day (Aug. 10, c. 1957): 1-10 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Picuris pueblo photos, San Lorenzo Saints Day (Aug. 10, c. 1957): 11-20 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Picuris pueblo photos, San Lorenzo Saints Day (Aug. 10, c. 1957): 21-30 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Picuris pueblo photos, San Lorenzo Saints Day (Aug. 10, c. 1957): 31-40 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Picuris pueblo photos, San Lorenzo Saints Day (Aug. 10, c. 1957): 41-48 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Picuris pueblo photos, miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Note on photos (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2004-094
  - Annual Review, 1977-78 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Review, 1979-80 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Review, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anthropology 124 Art and Culture, 1968-71 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anthropology 149 Anthropology of Development, class info, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anthropology 149 Anthropology of Development, course guide and reader, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anthropology 149 Anthropology of Development, literature, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anthropology 210 History and Modern Viewpoints, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anthropology 210 History and Modern Viewpoints, handouts and notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Anthropology 251, student project reports, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Aspects of Political Organization at Taos Pueblo [Siegel], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Beauclerk and Narby, "A Fieldguide to Indigenous Peoples Development," part 1, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Beauclerk and Narby, "A Fieldguide to Indigenous Peoples Development," part 2, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bibliographies, miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Biennial Review: correspondence and notes, 1966-68 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Folk Society, notes and paper by Siegel, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Four: The nature of strain (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Italian research, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Johansson, Sheila, "Morality, Welfare and Gender," 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Longitudinal study of the physical growth of Tucson, Arizona, school children [possibly by Francis J. Meaney], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mountain View project, interview reports, 1952-53 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Native American Preservation Act - written testimony, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Nutini, Hugo G. "Structural History: A Programmatic Synthesis of the Nomothetic and Idiographic Elements of Anthropological Studies," n.d. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Orlove, Benjamin S., "Cultural Ecology: A Critical Essay and a Bibliography," Institute of Ecology Publication No. 13, UC Davis, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Parma Project - notes, proposals, bibliographies, etc., 1972-78 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Parma Project - notes, proposals, bibliographies, etc., 1978-80 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Personal correspondence, 1978-83 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Publications, foreign (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Polgar, Steven - two papers, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Requests for material, 1977-78 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Responses to requests, 1970-72 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Review of D. Morris's Intimate Behavior, with correspondence, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sacred artifacts and skeletal remains - resource information (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Saltman, Michael, research plan and paper, ca. 1986 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Science articles, 1970-78 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Siegel - c.v. and biographical information (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Siegel - reprints (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Siegel, James, "Conservative Islam in Atjeh," 1962 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sociology 203 - notes, 1941 and n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Stanford Humanities Anthropology Conference, transcript of sessions, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Stanford Humanities Center, year end report, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - TA apprenticeship readings, Fall 1997 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - TA apprenticeship readings, Fall 1997 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Taos - interviews and observations, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Taos - assorted articles, 1949-72 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Textor, Robert B., "High Tech Bibliography," Stanford Project on the Human Impacts and Sociocultural Implications of High Technology, May 1989 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Wharton, Clifton R., "Risk, Uncerainty and the Subsistence Farmer," 1968 (Box 4, Folder 13)